Finding Aid for Williams family papers, 1838-1953
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Williams family papers 1838-1953
Williams family.
2 linear feet
86297 Aa 2
A. L. Williams family of Owosso, Michigan. Personal and business correspondence of A. L. Williams, Owosso, Michigan pioneer, railroad entrepreneur, and spiritualist; and personal letters of other members of the family, including May Williams Dewey, wife of E. O. Dewey (Thomas E. Dewey family); and miscellaneous newspaper clippings, business ledgers, and personal and business diaries concerning business affairs and daily activities; "spirit messages" received from departed family and others; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Williams family collection was received in two accessions. The first was the gift of Mr. and Mrs. Sherman E. Welch (donor no. 5174 ) in 1971; the second was the gift of Jane E. McCormick (donor no. 7144 ) in 1984 and 2001.
No additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The first member of the Williams family to come to Michigan was Oliver Williams (1774-1834). In 1808, Oliver, a native of Massachusetts, established a mercantile business at Detroit, trading supplies for furs. In 1815, he moved his family to Detroit and opened a hotel and boarding house called the Yankee. In 1819, Oliver moved to a site northwest of Pontiac, Michigan. It is said that the first school in the county was established in 1821 and operated out of his sheep shed.
In 1838, two of Oliver's sons, Alfred Leonzo and Benjamin Oliver, bought land and became the first settlers of what was to become Owosso, Michigan.
The Williams Family [Owosso] collection consists of 2 linear feet of material. It includes the personal and business papers of four generations of Williamses from 1838 to 1953. However, the bulk of the material relates to the family of Alfred Leonzo Williams between 1860 and 1890.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Shiawassee County.; Business records.; Dewey, Edmund Otis, 1861-1921.; Dewey family.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Olivet College.; Owosso (Mich.); Railroads--Michigan.; Shiawassee County (Mich.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Spiritualists--Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Owosso.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Log cabins.; Olivet College.; Williams, Alfred Leonzo, 1808-1886.
Contributors:
Dewey, May Williams.; Williams, Alfred Leonzo, 1808-1886.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Family papers
  - Family History (Box 1)
    The Family History file contains several family histories and genealogical charts. The genealogy compiled by Ephraim S. Williams in 1877 is the most complete.
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence is arranged chronologically. The earliest Correspondence, beginning in 1840, is mostly between Alfred and Benjamin, and their mother and brother Ephraim. Between 1860 and 1863, Alfred was usually away on railroad business. Thus, there is correspondence between him and his wife and children. Subjects include farm prices, prospects for the fall harvest, and family news. Especially interesting is his correspondence with son Schuyler. They discuss the outbreak of the Civil War, draft evaders in Detroit, and college life in Ann Arbor. Through the 1870s and 1880s, most of the correspondence is between Alfred's wife Harriet and their children who had married and moved away. It deals primarily with family news. However, other interesting correspondence in this period includes letters dealing with Alfred's 1885 application for a patent on his vapor bath and the courtship correspondence (1872-1873) of Emma Williams and William Kilpatrick, an Owosso attorney and later state senator. The correspondence of Florence (Flo) Kilpatrick, daughter of Emma and William, is also included. While attending Olivet College in the 1890's, she maintained a regular correspondence with Florence (Flossie) Ayers, a friend from Owosso. Their frequent letters covered a wide range of personal concerns and experiences.
    - 1840-1860 (Box 1)
    - 1861-1865 (Box 1)
    - 1866-1870 (Box 1)
    - 1871-1874 (Box 1)
    - 1875 (Box 1)
    - 1876-1878 (Box 1)
    - 1879-1880 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1882 (Box 1)
    - 1883-1885 (Box 1)
    - 1885 (A.L. Williams' patent) (Box 1)
    - 1886-1890 (Box 1)
    - 1891-1898 (Box 1)
    - 1899-1953 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea
    - General (includes advertisements, business cards, and programs) (Box 1)
    - Personal (includes poems, stories, and drawings) (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Business Papers, 12 folders (Box 1)
    The business papers include receipts, routine business correspondence and deeds (including the original 1838 deed to Alfred Williams in Owosso). There are also title abstracts, account statements, loan forms, contracts, litigation (St. Nicholas Bank v. Alfred Williams, et al, 1862), and a stock certificate for 500 shares of the American Non-Explosive Boiler Attachment Company.
  - Business Ledgers And Diaries, 13 vols. (Box 1)
    The thirteen volumes of Business Ledgers and Diaries deal mostly with the business affairs of Alfred L. Williams.
  - Printed
    - The Liverpool, London, and Paris Guide, Guion Line Steamers, ca. 1873 (Box 1)
    - Abury Illustrated, William Long, 1858 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    The Photographs are of two general types. First, there are several photographs of Olivet College and its students in the 1890's. Second, there are three family photographs: a portrait of Alfred L. Williams, a portrait of an unnamed young girl, and an informal group shot in front of a farmhouse.
  - Family correspondence, 1852-1881 (Box 2)
  - Spiritualist messages (Box 2)